On the morning of August the 6th, 1945,
the American bomber Inola Olleay took
off for the Japanese archipelago. In its
Bombay was an atomic device nicknamed
Little Boy. The target was Hiroshima, an
industrial city with 340,000
inhabitants. At 8:15 a.m., the bomb was
dropped, creating a blast equivalent to
15,000 tons of TNT.
A gigantic nuclear mushroom rose above
the city. The temperature at ground zero
reached 4,000°.
70,000 were killed outright.
The city was totally annihilated.
>> It was as if we dropped a million
conventional bombs on the city. 1
million bombs.
The irradiation would continue to claim
numerous victims for dozens of years.
The total death toll in Hiroshima was
140,000.
The level of devastation from one small
weapon that was unprecedented in
humankind.
3 days after Hiroshima, a second atomic
bomb was dropped over the city of
Nagasaki, immediately killing 45,000.
These two bombs dealt a final blow to
the Japanese Empire, which surrendered
on September the 2nd, 1945.
The Second World War was over. The
United States was hoisted to the rank of
superpower.
Am I proud?
I I think I think that the way the war
ended so fast and saved many lives, in
that sense, I'm proud of what I did. I'm
not proud of a mass destruction.
>> But what is less well known is that
Germany had been leading the way. The
Americans were convinced that Hitler was
on the point of acquiring a nuclear
weapon and they were going to do
everything to prevent him from getting
there first.
>> This is very important. If the Germans
get this bomb before we do, Hitler will
win and the world will be dominated by
the Third Reich for a thousand years.
Hitler had an 18-month start, so it was
urgent. The Americans launched the
biggest secret operation of all time, a
colossal budget of 26 billion, and the
world's best scientists, code name
Project Manhattan.
The scientists engaged on this project
were fanatic about trying to solve it
and make sure that it was going to work
and that would be delivered on time.
There was tremendous pressure on them.
>> The project was top secret. 600,000
people were working on ultra seccure
sites throughout the United States,
hidden away from the eyes of the world.
Not even the US Congress was kept in the
loop.
>> Security. Security. Security was the key
in Los Alamos. I mean, everybody lived
and breathed security 24/7 constantly.
>> An astonishing race against time played
out in parallel. This time between
themselves and their allies as the
Soviets too were desperate for the bomb.
This race at the end of the war about
brain power from the German scientists
and reanium was a great competition
between the allied forces
>> and the allies had no hesitation in
using spies.
>> He was one of the most cleverest and
most brilliant scientists ever to be
involved in that. Claus Fukes was
probably the most important spy ever in
the history of espionage.
>> We're going to reveal to you the story
of this incredible secret competition.
An insane race with no holes barred and
with the destiny of the world at stake.
Germany early 1930s. Adolf Hitler had
just been appointed chancellor of the
Reich.
Though the country had become militarily
one of the most powerful in the world,
it also led in another domain that of
science. Germany was a pioneer in
disciplines such as chemistry and
physics.
For almost 40 years, it had been the
nation with the most Nobel Prize
winners.
such as Max Plank, the energy
specialist, Albert Einstein, and a
certain Va Heisenberg, one of the most
brilliant atomic researchers in the
land, generally thought of as a genius.
To the eyes of the world, Germany seemed
to be an extremely scientifically
advanced country. In the world of
intelligence,
they had codes and enigma, the encoding
machine. In terms of weapons, they had
the most modern aircraft and Germany had
a place apart, a breeding ground for
science and scholars.
>> But Hitler's anti-Semitic laws led to
the exile of many brilliant scientists
including Albert Einstein who settled in
the USA.
It all began one day in August 1939 when
Einstein was vacationing on the east
coast on the residential Long Island.
His vacation would be less peaceful than
planned.
That day he received a visit from one of
his colleagues and friends, Leo Zelad, a
Jewish Hungarian physicist who had also
left his country when faced with the
rise of Nazism.
He had come to make a highly important
revelation to Einstein.
On the terrace of his holiday home, he
explained how Germany was exploiting a
new source of energy, uranium, which
could lead to the creation of
devastating weapons. Without delay,
Einstein decided to write a letter to
the president of the United States
himself, Franklin D. Roosevelt. And this
is what he explained. I understand that
Germany has actually stopped the sale of
uranium from the Czechoslovakian mines
which he has taken over. The uranium
will in the near future be converted
into a new source of energy. This new
phenomenon might also lead to bombs of a
new type being constructed. A single
bomb of this type carried by boat and
exploded in a port might very well
destroy the whole port together with
some of the surrounding territory.
>> It doesn't mince his words. He says that
the Germans are working on this project
and it will be enormously destructive.
>> He thinks it's very important that the
president be aware of this and
understand that this could mean the
beginning of some kind of German bomb
program.
>> Roosevelt became aware of the letter and
the information terrified him. He was
right to be worried
as at the same time events in Europe
were moving along pace. In September
1939, Hitler first sent his troops to
attack Poland, then to conquer France,
and finally to threaten Great Britain.
The Second World War was underway.
In just a few months, Hitler had
conquered a large part of Europe. But
with war looming, American public
opinion forced Roosevelt to remain
neutral.
Yet it was impossible to stand still and
watch as a nation as powerful as Germany
gained possession of a weapon of mass
destruction.
The USA needed absolutely to have the
same thing in order to defend itself
should the need arise, which is just
what Roosevelt told his advisers.
Roosevelt listens and says, "I see. What
you're telling me is that we have to be
careful that our neighbor doesn't blow
us up.
We'll do something about this," says the
president.
>> So as not to be left behind, Roosevelt
summoned scientists entrusted with a
feasibility study for the atomic bomb.
At that point, the project was very
small, just a dozen men and a budget of
barely $100,000.
But one event turned everything upside
down.
On December the 7th, 1941, Japan,
Germany's ally, attacked the US fleet at
its Pearl Harbor base in the Pacific.
The United States joined the war.
I ask
that the Congress declare
a state of war
has existed
between the United States and the
Japanese Empire.
>> Just days later, it was Hitler's turn to
declare war on the United States. Now
the country could become one of
Germany's targets.
>> The allies are very conscious that
Germany is an immense power both in
terms of its military and its
scientists. Uh they are frightened. They
knew that Hitler was a ruthless man that
he would not hesitate to use this bomb
if he had a chance. If they could get
the bomb first then they would probably
use it on London or Washington.
Building an atomic device became
Roosevelt's absolute priority, and he
was convinced that Germany and the USA
were locked in a race against the clock.
Whoever had the bomb first would win,
and according to the president, the
Reich already had a head start.
>> They might be as much as a year or a
year and a half ahead of the United
States program. And that could mean that
they could have a bomb by Christmas of
43, summer of 1944,
and it would be devastating
to make an atomic bomb, something no one
has ever done, and also claw back an
18-month lead. Roosevelt's challenge
appeared insane,
so he pulled out all the stops. In all,
more than 600,000 people were recruited.
Factories and entire towns were erected
in just months. In spanking new
laboratories, the world's best
scientists worked on the most absolute
secrets with unlimited resources. The
code name for this groundbreaking
military program was Project Manhattan.
At its head, two men with radically
different profiles. Leslie Groves, the
soldier, and Robert Oppenheimer, the
scientist.
Groves was chosen by Roosevelt himself
to run the program. The man had an
extraordinary profile. He was both a
general and an engineer, and his
experience was unquestioned. He had
built the Pentagon, the biggest
headquarters of any of the world's
military forces.
>> General Groves has been called the
indispensable man of the Manhattan
Project. He was a dynamo. He had more
energy. He was more decisive than anyone
among his peers. Or at least it seems
so. He said any difficult problem should
be solved within one hour.
>> He was a tall, bulky, doineering,
powerful. He said, "All right." And he
immediately went to work. His first
mission to find the man to lead the
scientists. He selected Oppenheimer, a
brilliant physicist who taught in
California at Berkeley. But his choice
stunned the scientific community because
Oppenheimer wasn't seen as the best in
his field.
>> People said, "Groves is choosing
Oppenheimer. That's very strange.
Oppenheimer has never he's never
administered anything. he's never
accomplished what some of these other
scientists uh there were already Nobel
Prize winners uh participating in the
early stages of of the project. But
Groves always chose younger people who
still had a lot of energy and ambition
to achieve a goal and he saw that in
Oenheimer. He saw it immediately. The
choice was all the more surprising in
that Oenheimer's style was far removed
from that of the authoritarian and
uncompromising groves.
>> Oppenheimer in contrast he looks like a
very sensitive poet which he was. He
carried in his pocket the poetry of
Bodilair.
He was uh really an oporadic character.
He was a philosopher. He spoke seven
languages. He studied the Indian
scriptures. He was um a hugely sensitive
man.
>> Despite significant differences between
the two men, Roosevelt put all his trust
in the duo and gave them cart blanch.
>> Groves's responsibilities from the
outset were ones of uh extraordinary
power. He had uh the full resources of
the US government behind him. Uh any
amount of money that he wanted. um he
could have anything that he needed. He
saw early on that there was going to be
a competition for resources and thus he
needed first priority on any material
that he wanted. If it was copper or gold
or silver or anything, he had to have
first priority.
Groves's first problem. Where to create
the infrastructure to make the bomb?
They couldn't build it in a laboratory
in a city. The equipment needed was
colossal. The uranium enrichment plant
alone was 1 kilometer long. And there
were other demands.
Groves wanted the sites to be isolated
because they were top secret. He didn't
want people to know. They were also
dealing with firstofind facilities
uh building a nuclear reactor uh that
would get to be uh two and 3,000 degrees
in the center and you know for all they
knew that could blow up. They had not
built one of these. you know, they had
to plan um for a buffer zone to make
sure that there were no people in
anywhere near these facilities in case
something went wrong.
In addition, Groves didn't want the bomb
built on just one site, but on three. As
being unknown territory, they had to try
several methods.
A first immense complex was built in
Oakidge, Tennessee to make uranium. Then
a second in Hanford near Seattle to
produce plutonium. They had yet to find
the ideal location for the third site,
the most crucial, the one where the bomb
would be assembled.
And that required an even more isolated,
even more secret location. Groves was at
a loss.
Oppenheimer had an idea. In November
1942, he took Groves to the American
Southwest, New Mexico.
>> Oenheimer knew the area because he had a
ranch in New Mexico and loved New
Mexico. It was it's a beautiful place.
It's it's gorgeous. And um they go
around and Groves is saying, "No, not
this place. Not this place. Not this
place. Do you?" And he says to
Oppenheimer, "Do you know any other
places?" And Oenheimer says, "Well,
there's this school. There's this Los
Alamos Ranch School up on the mesa over
here." Groves and Oppenheimer come upon
this scene of boys out exercising and
immediately Gro said, "This is it.
That's it." So they closed the school.
They got the boys off off and they took
over what was already a beginning of a
place to live and stay.
It was here at Los Alamos on these
extreme lands at 2500 m altitude that
the largest atomic laboratory was
created.
And it was here that Oppenheimer
intended to bring the world's best
scientists.
The problem was he had to convince them.
How could he persuade them to drop
everything and move to the middle of
nowhere for an unspecified period? More
pertinently, how could Oppenheimer get
them to work on a project that no one
knew would even work?
That's part of Groves's and
Oppenheimer's dilemma.
I mean, they don't know that it's going
to work. Maybe it wouldn't work. Maybe
it would be a failure. They pressed the
button,
nothing happened.
I mean, maybe, you know, maybe it
failed. Maybe it was a failure.
Oenheimimer had a tricky task. So to
recruit the best brains, he took his
pilgrim staff and crisscrossed the
United States. For a year, one after
another, he tried to convince them one
after another with an irrefutable
argument. This is what he said.
>> That what they were working on might not
only end this war, but possibly all
future wars.
So he put it to them in a way that was
drawing upon their patriotism, drawing
upon their visceral hatred of Germany
and Hitler and his anti-semitic regime
and it was quite compelling for for many
of the scientists.
Though Einstein wasn't authorized to
take part in the project because of his
pacifist leanings, Oppenheimer's gamble
paid off. He had assembled the best
scientists in the world, among them 20
Nobel Prize winners. In the spring of
1943, they came to the New Mexico desert
and Los Alamos.
Meanwhile, what was a boarding school
for boys had become a real town. Mobile
homes as far as the eye could see. There
were offices, assembly, workshops,
laboratories, as well as a hospital and
supermarkets.
An almost normal town where security was
omniresent.
Barbed wire all around. Military police
patrols around the clock. In all, 7,000
people lived here.
Along with the soldiers and scientists
were all the personnel needed to keep a
town running, laborers and
administrators.
There were also housewives who had
followed their husbands and their
children.
Dimas Chavez was six when he moved to
Los Alamos in August 1943. His father
had just been hired to build more
laboratories. When he arrived, he saw
that he had just entered the most secret
town on earth.
First of all, we came to a a main gate
that was manned by armed military police
and dad had already filled out all the
appropriate paperwork and so forth that
authorized him to come to Los Alamos.
And then they took pictures of us. So,
we had to have an ID badge. And uh the
MP told my father, he said, "Okay, now
get in your vehicle and proceed on this
road." And there will be another
checkpoint about a mile down the road
and you are going to be given a certain
amount of time when you leave here to
when you get there. And if you don't get
in there in the prescribed period of
time, people will come after you. I I
didn't know what in the world was going
on. If if dad had a flat tire or what
have you, what would happen to us?
Fortunately, everything went fine. We
slipped right in.
>> At the same time, a young soldier from
New York arrived at Los Alamos.
His name was Benjamin Bees and he was
19. Benjamin had studied physics at
university for 2 years before joining
the army. One day, his officers proposed
him as assistant physicist on a military
project. He had no idea that he was
going to be working on the atom bomb.
The program was top secret. Yet, he
accepted the job. He was expecting a
military base. But when he got there, he
was stunned. There were scientists
everywhere.
>> We were in in the middle of nowhere
uh in a in a city that was just being
built, but and there were a lot of
civilians from all over the world,
mostly from Europe and America. There
were imagine imagine all the world
scientists were there. They were all
physics people and mathematicians and
everyone I knew was was an interesting
person.
Benjamin understood that his mission
would be linked to science. Like
himself, 99% of employees didn't know
what they were working on. That was
General Groves's aim to keep the secret.
>> It was the biggest secret of the war. It
is so it is said and um the very fact
that there was a bomb program you know
is a secret in itself and had the
Germans known that the Americans were
working on an atomic bomb maybe they
would have uh done more than they did.
>> Groves was obsessed by the notion that
Hitler might get the bomb first. Germany
led the world in science. He knew that
and things were getting urgent. The man
about whom he was weriest was the famous
atomic physicist Vanna Heisenberg. He
had stayed with Hitler rather than
choose exile.
He was the German scientist Grove saw as
the greatest threat.
>> If anyone would be in charge of this
program, it would be he.
And that if anyone would be able to
think his way through to a bomb, it
would be he.
Groves feared Heisenberg's talents in
this race against time. So he stepped up
security. To keep things secret, he
imposed job compartmentalization.
Each person from scholar to laborer
would have only one task to carry out
and would not be authorized to talk
about it. Information was thus reduced
to a minimum and nobody knew the
finality of the project. work conditions
so surprising that people began to
wonder.
>> Dad had access to many, many, many
restricted areas.
But did he know what was going on? No.
He had a job to do. He had a a hole to
dig there or something to move over
there or what have you. And as soon as
he was finished, he would be changed to
another area. We would talk about it,
but dad would immediately say, "You're
not supposed to know. I'm not supposed
to know. Don't say anything about it."
Period. So it would just end like that.
>> I was immediately given a job and my
boss was a Brit was from from England
and he had just he was a professor in
England and he was a physics professor.
So I knew that that I was doing physics
but I had no idea what it was of course.
But after a few weeks spent with
renowned British scientists, Benjamin
was let in on the secret when he was
transferred to the explosives
department.
He learned that he was building an
atomic bomb.
>> I was blowing up things. I had steel
tubes and I had explosives and I had a
um photographic
technique to measure the timing of the
explosions. But mainly we were just
blowing up things to seeing how they
survived under under explosions.
That's what I was doing. Just testing mi
materials for for uh their ability to
withstand an explosion.
I was very happy. It was very exciting
to know that I was doing real physics
and here I was in the army with the
world exploding around me. Uh people
were dying all over the world and I was
doing physics. I couldn't believe my
luck.
Benjamin was now among the 1% of
initiates.
Among this minority, the rules were
drastic. The scientists were strictly
forbidden to talk about the bomb even
with their wives at home in the evening.
And between themselves, they had to use
coded language.
>> You couldn't say bomb. It was called It
was called the gadget. The word bomb was
never used in public. None. No, none of
those words. efficient, fusion,
uh, chain reaction, neutron, all those
words were never used outside the tech
area.
All over the camp, giant signs provided
reminders of the ground rules.
Well, I was dying to tell what was going
on, but I knew I shouldn't. It was
certainly a temptation
to say what was going on. A secret was
really important, and we knew that.
>> Despite these constraints, Americans
hurried to be part of the project. The
country was at the time undergoing a
serious economic depression. The Great
Depression had pushed unemployment up to
its highest level. Here was the
assurance of a job and a home paid for
by the state. Deus' father didn't
hesitate for a second. After years of
uncertainty, working at Los Alamos
allowed him to look after his family.
>> It was his job. Uh he had no other job.
And my gosh, I mean, where else could
you live on a rent where we our rent was
$16 a month at the log cabin? Uh, our
food was uh available through military
uh prices and so forth. Uh, my dad
wasn't rolling in a lot of money. Uh,
but what he made, he he took care of us.
>> An everyday routine rapidly fell into
place. The children attended school.
There was a cinema, a theater, and a few
shops. Enough to keep the inhabitants
busy as they were not allowed to leave
town. Each found entertainment where he
could.
There was a lot of sports. There was uh
men got involved with basketball, with
softball, with baseball.
a scientist who had uh musical ability
formed bands.
Music was an outlet. Uh there was a
variety of bands that uh formed and
there was dancing every weekend, Fridays
and Saturdays. Everybody danced.
But even on Saturday nights, Big Brother
wasn't far away.
>> The bartenders were um agents who were
listening to their conversations. And if
someone had gotten um a little too drunk
and loose u with his conversation and
was talking too much about what he was
working on, he would be quickly whisked
away from the bar.
And for those who were a little too
chatty, there was no second chance.
>> If there was someone who was a security
risk, uh that person would be um sent to
some other assignment such as in the
Illusian Islands in Alaska. I mean, they
would be getting they would get rid of
them. Um but they couldn't just let them
go free to uh back to civilian life.
they go somewhere, they could keep tabs
on them.
>> In this highsecurity environment, the
scientists worked hard. But by January
1944, one year after Project Manhattan
had begun, panic had set in. They still
didn't have a bomb. It wasn't even
possible to say whether they'd have one
before the Germans. And Groves had a
major new problem to face as after
Germany, a second rival had appeared in
this race against time. But this time it
was an ally,
the Soviet Union. For months, the
country had been struggling to cope with
the bloody German invasion.
Operation Barbarasa had begun on June
22nd, 1941.
4 million Axis soldiers dispatched to
take the USSR by surprise. The fighting
was merciless. But amidst all the chaos,
one man was worried about another
threat, a physicist, Gorgi Fleof. He had
noticed that a flood of articles written
by German and American scholars about
radioactive elements had suddenly dried
up. He suspected that researchers were
engaged in making an atomic bomb.
So he went to the library to see is
there anything in the American journals
or other journals and he found there
wasn't anything and he looked at the
German journals and saw everything on
nuclear fishision had disappeared. So he
concluded like the Sherlock Holmes story
that the dog that doesn't bark in the
night gives the clue that something must
be going on.
Then in April 1942, he wrote a letter to
Stalin to warn of the consequences of
the development of such a weapon.
The results will exceed what we now know
so totally that there will be no need to
determine who was to blame for the fact
that this work has been neglected in our
country.
So in turn, in early 1943, Stalin
launched a program to develop an atomic
bomb. Nothing like the Manhattan
project. Only a hundred or so scientists
were hired and research began here in
this tent outside Moscow.
The Manhattan project was the
Rolls-Royce.
The Soviet project wasn't even a Model T
Ford. It was a push bike.
The scientists working there did so
mainly with paper and pencil.
They were living in great material
poverty. There was no nuclear reactor
and there wasn't even any uranium, much
less plutonium.
There were no raw materials for a bomb.
The Soviets had none of that. But they
knew what they could do if they had the
resources.
The USSR, it must be said, was ruined.
The war had already cost them millions
of lives. A Soviet counteroffensive was
underway on every front. All available
resources were mobilized. Scientific
research was far from being Stalin's
priority.
>> The Soviet Union was a third world
country, incomparably poorer than the
United States. There were therefore few
resources to allocate to research,
whether fundamental or applied.
Everything went to the war effort.
>> There was, however, one area where the
USSR excelled that would prove crucial.
Espionage.
And one of their spies was particularly
productive. He sent them all the
American advances on the bomb. He
managed to spy in the most secure town
in the world, Los Alamos. His name was
Klaus Fuks.
Claus Fukes was probably the most
important spy ever in the history of
espionage because he was one of the most
cleverest and most brilliant scientists
ever to be involved in that.
Fuks was of German stock from a
middle-class family with a minister
father.
At 17, when Hitler seized power,
>> he became an opponent of the Nazi and
joined the Communist Party.
>> He makes it very clear, I think, that
one of the biggest threats he sees to
German society is the growth of the
right-wing and Nazism. And I think that
he believes that the Communist Party are
the only people who will stand up to the
Nazis. And
for a man like Fuks, that would have
been an really fundamental commitment in
his life.
A confirmed communist, he left Nazi
Germany for Great Britain, where he
began to study physics. He obtained
British nationality and his profile as a
physicist grew quickly. He was then
recruited to work on the British atomic
bomb project that began in 1940, 2 years
before the Manhattan project. But his
political convictions led him straight
to the Russian embassy in London, where
he offered his services to the USSR.
>> As soon as Germany attacked the Soviet
Union, he went to the Soviet embassy in
London and said, "I know about this. I
can tell you about my work." He knows
that work is being done to create a
uranium atom bomb and he's invited to
work on that program and he believes
that he has a duty to tell the communist
party, the GRU and the Soviet Union. At
that point, he has become a spy.
In 2 years, Fuks passed to the USSR 570
pages of calculations and descriptions
of the construction of an atomic bomb.
It was the result of everything Great
Britain had discovered. But he went even
further because in late 1942,
General Groves asked the Allies to send
their best scientists to the USA to
accelerate research on the bomb. Fuks,
the eminent physicist, was also invited
along on the trip. In November 1943, he
arrived in the United States. The
Russian spy was taken on board the
Manhattan project. There, he would have
access to all top secret information.
The Allies had no idea they were being
spied on.
Groves had one obsession. Though his
bomb would not be finished for several
months, he still didn't know whether
Hitler was ready to launch his own. To
find out, he had to interrogate the
scientists who had remained in Germany.
First among them, Vienna Heisenberg, who
was heading up the German program. The
only way to get to him was to send men
into the field, but that would have to
wait for spring 1944 and the liberation
of Europe.
Early in the morning of the 6th of June,
130,000 men landed on beaches in
Normandy. It was the largest military
operation of all time.
Among the Allied soldiers, there were
also American civilians, men whose
objective wasn't to liberate Europe from
the Nazi yoke.
They were scientists in soldiers
uniforms. 20 of them sent by Groves
personally. Their mission was to find
out the exact state of advancement of
the German bomb.
>> He needed to have his own intelligence
and counterintelligence forces. He
needed to have his own eyes and ears,
his own men there.
>> This special new kind of spy unit was
the Alsos mission. It was headed by a
certain Samuel Goodsmid. This
45-year-old Netherlander taught physics
at the University of Michigan, but
during the 1930s had rubbed shoulders
with the most brilliant German
scientists. Some were even his friends,
privileged contacts that could come in
very useful in obtaining information.
He fits a lot of parameters for the
ideal person to go track down the
scientists and interrogate them.
Following the advance of the Allied
troops in France, Goodsid and his men
arrived on November the 25th, 1944 in a
place of particular interest, Strasborg.
The city had become a showcase of the
Reich for scientific research. This is
where Alsos hoped to pick up the trail
of Vera Heisenberg. It was he who could
give them information on the German
bomb. On arrival at the University of
Strasborg, Goodsmith found documents and
an address that can enable him to locate
Heisenberg.
Good discovers, and it's very exciting
news, that Heisenberg, the central
figure he's looking for, is not in
Berlin, which is being bombed to
destruction at that point in the war,
but has moved to Hesshingan, where in
fact in the Black Forest, the uh what's
what there is of the German bomb program
has been moved.
Hessing, a small town that Goodsmith and
his men would never have considered, was
lost in the black forest some 60 km from
Stoodgard.
According to the Alsos mission, it was
the perfect place to hide a laboratory.
Goodsmith knew he was close to reaching
his goal, but had further surprises in
store. As he wasn't the only one
interested in German atomic research, he
had to contend with the French. He
realized that when on April the 24th,
1945, the Alsos mission finally arrived
in sight of Heshingan, the town was just
the other side of a bridge. But the
problem was another army was already
stationed there and ready to enter the
town. The French Liberation Army.
Nothing serious. They were allies after
all. But when it came to head-hunting
scientists, it was every man for
himself. And the French after 5 years of
war were only just beginning their
nuclear program.
>> The French have their own intelligence
program and would like to capture some
of these scientists for post-war France.
So there is a lot of competition to get
to these scientists first.
>> If the French were to capture
Heisenberg, they would in all
probability keep him to themselves.
It was a tricky situation. It was vital
that the ALS mission prevent the first
French army from advancing. But what
could they do? The Americans tried
bluffing.
>> They do is say, "Wait, it's about to be
bombed. You don't want to go in there.
Our planes are coming." And the uh the
French officers say, "All right, we'll
wait." And the also people run in.
As a result, the first army stood firm
and didn't enter Hesshingan. The Alsos
mission hurried on in. At the address
found in Strasburg University, they
found a church. And when they searched
it, they hit the jackpot. In the crypt,
Goodsmith found a secret laboratory and
a huge reactor. But amid the drama, it
turned out it wasn't a bomb at all, but
an atomic battery that could only be
used to make electricity. The ALS team
was relieved.
Two weeks later, it picked up
Heisenberg.
He confirmed that Germany was still a
long way off mastering atomic energy.
There's nothing there. There's no
program. There's no effort. There's no
collaboration of German science, the
German military, and German industry to
make a Manhattan project of their own.
Hitler didn't support the atomic bomb
work in Germany. He felt that it wasn't
necessary that they were going to finish
the war. Heisenberg had told Hitler it
was going to take 10 years and you know
millions of dollars. Uh and Hitler said
that's not worth it. We'll be done with
the war long long before then.
>> The Americans have therefore nothing
further to fear from the Germans. But
what they do discover is they have a new
adversary, an ultra determiner rival.
They hadn't considered one which will
turn out to be particularly dangerous.
The USSR for the Soviets too hoped to
scoop up as many scientists as they
could from Germany along with the
material to build their bomb. The
Americans had to play a close game in
Germany. A new arms race had begun.
Even though the war is not yet over,
um our ally
uh there are some indications that um
some people already see the Russians,
the Soviet Union as the next
competition,
the next potential enemy,
>> especially since the Soviets had also
organized a scientific mission to loot
on German soil. It was led by the highly
motivated, brilliant physicist Julie
Kerton.
>> Keraton was totally starved of all the
material he needed to experiment and to
build and was the man in the field who
was able to say, "I want this
installation. Dismantle it and send it
to the Soviet Union. I want this
material. We definitely need that
oscilloscope."
This time the Russians were every bit
the equal of the American mission.
The resources that the Soviets poured
into Alsos were colossal compared to
their general state of poverty. The
greatest Soviet atomic scientists went
to Germany. For the two months they were
hunting German scientists and material.
The Soviet program ground to a halt.
Everyone had gone to Germany led by
Karon.
The reason that the USSR had spared no
expense on this mission was because
building an atomic bomb required uranium
and the country didn't have enough. Only
7 tons when 200 were needed and it
happened to be found in Germany.
You don't go looking for an atomic bomb
sitting on a shelf with a pretty bow
tied around it.
You go looking in the industrial bases
for the raw material of uranium to try
to accelerate the Soviet program. But
the Soviets know that the Germans have a
stock of uranium
for one simple reason. The Germans
occupied Czechoslovakia in 1938 and the
only big uranium mine known at the time
was in Yuakimal in Czechoslovakia.
So the Soviets did accumulate uranium
during the war.
But the Americans, who still didn't yet
have the bomb, didn't want the USSR to
find that uranium.
>> Groves understands, yes, the so the US
will have the bomb, but he wants to make
sure the American monopoly will last as
long as possible
because it's because that makes America
more powerful.
The thing is at the beginning of 1945
the Americans were already lagging
behind. While they were stuck in the
Arden, the Red Army with its scientists
had already entered Germany from the
east and was advancing on Berlin.
The Soviets were liable to get their
hands on the uranium stocks first in
this factory close to Berlin which
produced it. But General Groves had
foreseen everything.
They discover in Strasburg a lot of
documents relating to the German atomic
project. And apparently in those
documents it said that uh there was a
group at the um our gazelle shaft plant
in Oranianburg that produced the metal
for the project. So he then requested
that the uh US Army Air Force bomb the
plant.
>> Make a good run now. Steve,
>> on March the 15th, 1945, 600 US bombers
dropped 1,500 tons of explosives and
incendiary bombs on the plant. The
unprecedented scale of the bombing
destroyed the entire stock of uranium.
100 tons in all. A clear act of
hostility against his Soviet ally.
>> The plant wasn't part of the German war
effort. It made uranium oxides, but it
was just to stop the Soviets having it.
And it was Groves in person who gave the
order to the head of the US Army Air
Force to flatten that factory. That
shows the extent of the power visited
upon him. And it was also to deprive the
Soviets of it. The Cold War hadn't
started, but they were intervening
directly to deny an ally access to
essential material.
>> The Americans went even further to
deprive the Russians of this uranium.
This time, they clearly flouted
international laws. One month after the
bombing of Iranianberg, the Alsos men
finally made it to Germany and found out
from captured German scientists that the
real stock of uranium was kept under
guard in Stasoot, 200 km from the
capital, a treasure trove of 1,200 tons
of uranium. It was imperative that they
retrieve it before the Russians.
The problem was the town was part of the
Russian occupied zone as laid out in the
Yelta agreements.
Groves couldn't care less and ordered
his men to dash to Stashford.
In secret, in the middle of the night,
they loaded the uranium into the
vehicles.
Wave upon wave of trucks took the stock
to Great Britain. When the Red Army
arrived several days later, there was
nothing left.
The Soviet Union knew what had happened
and they made some protests not about
the seizing of the uranium but about the
fact that US troops had crossed into an
area that was supposed to be part of the
Soviet zone of occupation.
>> They had no right to do that. Are you
sure they've no right to do that?
The rule of law in war is that when I
beat my enemy, I have the right to
spoils. Who beat the German army in
Saxony? The US army. Consequently, it
can be considered as the spoils of war.
That's how the Americans justified it.
In truth, of course, it was a violation
of the Yala agreements as they should
leave all the infrastructure. This isn't
infrastructure. It's raw materials. So,
they were playing with words. But quite
honestly, Groves was an extremely
straight guy, fairly brutal. He couldn't
care less about the legal quibbling.
What he wants is for the Soviets not to
have those 1,200 tons of uranium.
But Groves didn't totally achieve his
aim because at the same time, the
Russians too found something.
Julie Kerron learned that there was
uranium in another town called Nistat.
But that's a very common name in
Germany. 20 towns shared the name and 10
of them were in the Soviet zone.
So they searched them all with a fine
toothcomb.
>> Kon himself went there with his little
geer counter. He went there with Zeldic
and they began 1 2 3 4 5 nothing. 6 7 8
9 nothing. They get desperate and
there's only one left and bingo that's
the one. Noata
in a large leather tannery which had
already been requisitioned by the
Soviets.
There Katon discovered a warehouse with
huge piles of casks.
The problem was they were full of lead.
The lead reduced the radiation and
prevented Keraton's Geiger counter from
working.
>> So there was nothing conclusive.
He wondered whether the clocking was
down to natural background
radioactivity.
So he dropped it and left.
Then he had a bad night's sleep and told
his colleagues, "We're going back
there." And I think it was on the third
visit that finally he had the lead casks
unsealed and saw his Geiger counter go
through the roof as he had found the 100
tons of highlyenriched uranium oxide
which was immediately sent to the Soviet
Union.
100 tons is enough to start a program.
Not quite enough, but a good start.
And the Russians were able to make great
strides as they were soon to receive the
manual of how to make a turnkey atomic
bomb. This was passed on by their spy
Klaus Fouse who had infiltrated the
Allies. After spending 8 months in a New
York laboratory, he became one of the
best theoreticians in the world. This
knowledge was vital to the research into
the making of the gadget. So he managed
in 1944 to be transferred to Los Alamos.
There he obtained a key position, more
importantly one that afforded him an
overall view of the bomb.
>> He was in the theoretical division
working on this absolutely key problem
of how to detonate a plutonium bomb,
what the implosion mechanism is. And the
theoretical division um was rather open
to discussion. So Fuks was in a position
actually to have a very clear idea of
the design of the bomb of the problems
that would arise in using plutonium for
a bomb.
Fuks worked hard 18 hours a day. He was
respected by his colleagues even the
most eminent and as a good spy he
managed to win their trust.
>> He was a very quiet law-abiding
um person. He uh you know he babysat for
the children of his colleagues at Los
Alamos. Uh he was uh very polite,
reserved. He seemed to be the last
person to um uh to be a spy, but of
course he was the first person to be a a
spy.
>> He knew
so many details. He knew, you know, what
uh the bomb casing looked like, what the
inside lenses look like, what the
initiator looked like, all of these
details that um most people in the
project wouldn't have known all of it,
but he had been so trusted and he was so
involved in in the work that he had
knowledge of this.
Fuks was able to pass all this top
secret information to Moscow thanks to
the privilege afforded his status.
Exceptionally, he was authorized to
leave Los Alamos.
His contact was Harry Gold, an American
communist recruited by the Soviet secret
services. For a year, Fuks and his
messenger met up sporadically.
But on June the 6th, 1945, the meeting
between the two men was capital. Fuks
handed gold the documents that would
save the USSR 18 months of research and
$26 billion.
>> Fuks leaves Los Alamos in his car,
drives out to Santa Fe. It's in the
evening. They go to a bridge
that's in a public park just outside of
Santa Fe. It's overlooking the town. And
then um folks hands over a
large bundle of documents.
>> Folks supplied uh a description a
detailed description of the plutonium
bomb and with all the relevant
dimensions and all the different
components of the bomb. Uh and this was
extremely important information which
the Soviet uh scientists had no way of
discovering themselves by that point
because they had no samples of plutonium
to an analyze. Uh
and the Soviet scientists decided they
would take this design as the basis for
their own first bomb.
That same day, Fuks warned them the bomb
was nearly ready and would be tested in
the near future. Several weeks later, on
July the 17th, 1945, the Allied powers
convened in Potam near Berlin,
represented by Harry Truman, the new US
president, Joseph Stalin, and Winston
Churchill.
Germany had surrendered two months
earlier, and the allies had to prepare
the post-war period and split the
spoils. The Soviet leader thought he was
in a strong position with the Red Army
controlling most of Central Europe. But
what Stalin didn't know was that Truman
held a major trump card, the atomic bomb
test the previous day.
Just after sunrise on July the 16th,
1945 at Alamogordo in the New Mexico
desert. In the greatest secrecy, the
first nuclear explosion in history was
about to be detonated. Testing an
implosion device containing 6 kilos of
plutonium, code named Trinity. The bomb
was so complex that nobody knew whether
or not it would work.
>> 5 4 3 2 1 zero ignition.
>> At 5:30 a.m., the bomb's detonation
released the energy equivalent to 21
kilotons of TNT.
The explosion was visible over a 300 km
radius. It was a total success. The USA
had the ultimate weapon.
Truman, who had just arrived at the
Potam conference, heard the news via a
coded telegram from General Groves.
Operated on this morning, diagnosis not
yet complete, but results seem
satisfactory and already exceed
expectations. Truman didn't grasp the
importance of this message at his first
meeting with Stalin. Negotiations
continued, but then Truman received a
detailed account of Trinity's explosion.
He saw that the bomb was a total
success.
Doctor has just returned most
enthusiastic and confident that little
boy is as husky as his big brother. The
light in his eyes discernable from here
to Highold. And I could have heard his
screams from here to my farm.
The situation was turned on its head.
Truman now knew that he was in a
position of strength. He even decided to
announce the news to Stalin.
It happened quickly. It lasted a minute.
Stalin was leaving the conference hall.
Truman ran after him and casually
informed him,
"We've just tested a bomb of terrifying
effectiveness that is capable of
destroying a whole city."
Stalin merely said,
"Thank you." That's all.
>> Truman had in his hands a revolutionary
diplomatic weapon. His message to Stalin
was clear.
>> You have the world's biggest
conventional army, most probably the
best, the Red Army and its 300
divisions.
You think you hold the Trump card. But I
show up with a Trump that dwarfs yours.
So when it comes to talks, it's no
longer you who has the big stick. It's
me. This is act one of what was called
nuclear diplomacy.
Now it was the United States who could
dictate conditions. With this bomb,
Truman had no need for Soviet help in
obtaining Japan surrender.
He even brushed Stalin aside at the
signature of the allies final
declaration. An insult to the Soviet
leader. The Cold War began in Potdam.
4 days after the end of the conference
and only three weeks after the Trinity
test, the United States launched their
two atomic bombs on the Japanese Empire.
The first on Hiroshima was a uranium
bomb. The second over Nagasaki was a
plutonium bomb. They ushered in the
threat of a nuclear war, a major risk to
the future of modern civilization. After
the United States, seven other countries
managed to acquire nuclear weapons.
The USSR in 1949, Great Britain 3 years
later, France in 1960.
This race for the ultimate weapon
considerably changed relationships
between the great powers. Since they
have obtained the means of mutually
assured destruction, they are forced to
resort to diplomacy. That's why it's
called a nuclear deterrent.
Today, the issue is no longer how to win
the war.
But how to avoid the war?